<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/index/magazine.staging.csumb.edu/news/2011/oct/31/will-win" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Magazine</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/index/magazine.staging.csumb.edu/news/2011/oct/31/will-win</link>
    <description></description>
    <language>en</language>
          <item>
    <title>The Joy of Cycling</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/jun/2/joy-cycling</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	Student advocate pushes for&amp;nbsp;&amp;ldquo;Bike-Friendly University&amp;rdquo; status&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	When Bernard Green found his father&amp;rsquo;s old road bike in the back of the garage, his life changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Bernard and a bicycle&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/164/attachments/news/images/13-bernard_0_0.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right; width:300px; height:489px&quot; /&gt;&amp;ldquo;It was like flying,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;I loved feeling the wind rush by.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	His dad made him a deal &amp;ndash; keep up biking, and he&amp;rsquo;d buy Bernard his own road bike. The deal stuck and before long Bernard was cycling competitively at the LA Velodrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	After a year of track racing, Bernard felt the competition was taking away from the joy of riding. So he changed gears, became a bicycling advocate, and focused on sharing that joy with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The summer after his freshman year at CSUMB, Bernard returned to his hometown of Los Angeles and took a full-time internship with LA Bike Trains, an organization that helps new riders feel more comfortable commuting on bikes by organizing group rides or &amp;ldquo;bike trains.&amp;rdquo; The trains cover various routes through the city on weekday mornings. The pace is easy, the atmosphere social, and new riders find safety in numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s basically a moving bike party,&amp;rdquo; he said. As an intern, the Human Communication major helped the organization with its website, with fundraising, and with screening potential bike train &amp;ldquo;conductors.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	That summer he also gained certification as an instructor with the League of American Bicyclists. With that experience and credential under his belt, Bernard came back to CSUMB and founded the Monterey Bike Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Bernard describes the work of the project in three parts: First, educating cyclists by offering traffic safety and bike maintenance classes. Second, advocating for better cycling facilities and bike-friendly policies on campus and in Seaside and Marina. Finally, strengthening the cycling community through group rides and activities that connect new cyclists to more knowledgeable and experienced riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	His goal is for CSUMB to be officially recognized by the League of American Bicyclists as a bike-friendly campus by the time he graduates in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	After graduation, Bernard sees himself moving to the Pacific Northwest and studying urban planning in graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Ultimately, Bernard wants to contribute to a larger movement toward sustainability. He envisions a time when a sustainable lifestyle will be the status quo, and people would have to go out of their way to live unsustainably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;And the bike is one way to do that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Liz MacDonald&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photo by Randy Tunnell&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/65">Student Profile</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/16">Student Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/22">Sustainability</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 17:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21367 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Class Notes</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/class-notes</link>
    <description> &lt;h5&gt;
	1997&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Mary Olea Lesher&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Liberal Studies) is a retired public school teacher and author of a new book, &amp;ldquo;Return to the Soul of Your Child&amp;rdquo; (available on Amazon). Also a musician, Mary has recorded and produced eight original music CDs (available on her website, gracefulroadmusic.com). She is a member of the Monterey County Composers&amp;rsquo; Forum. She and her husband of 47 years, Richard, live in Salinas. She enjoys spending time with her grandchildren, playing guitar and creating new music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Christine Nieto&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Liberal Studies) has been an assessment solutions consultant for CTB/McGraw-Hill since 1998. She is a former member of the U.S. Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	1999&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Sarah Lerma&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) is a career/transfer center coordinator at Monterey Peninsula College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2000&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Nicole Mendoza Loeser&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Teledramatic Arts &amp;amp; Technology) is a curriculum and catalog specialist at San Jose State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2001&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Tracy Burke&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) is an account executive for the Monterey County Weekly, serving clients in the Ryan Ranch business park of Monterey. She volunteers with several organizations and has served on the boards of the Professional Women&amp;rsquo;s Network of Monterey and the Salinas Valley Business Women&amp;rsquo;s Network. She also has been director of the Kid&amp;rsquo;s Zone at the Oldtown Holiday Parade of Lights for five years. Tracy and her fianc&amp;eacute; recently launched a business, locationsscouting.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Vincent Suich&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Management &amp;amp; International Entrepreneurship) started The Sox Box with his wife, Athena, in 2009. The company donates 20 percent of its profits to the Independence Fund, a nonprofit organization that directly supports wounded, ill and injured service members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2003&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Carrie Drouin&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) has joined the Washington office of the Navajo Nation, where she serves as a government and legislative affairs associate. After earning a law degree at Golden Gate University, she was employed by DNA-People&amp;rsquo;s Legal Services, a nonprofit that provides free legal help in civil matters to low-income people in three Southwestern states and seven Native American nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Christopher Eichermueller&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Telecommunications, Multimedia and Applied Computing) recently moved to Germany to begin his new career as a sales engineer for the information technology services company Autotask. Previously, Christopher was a brewer for Devil&amp;rsquo;s Canyon Brewing Company in San Carlos. He earned a Master of Business Administration degree from Ashford University in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Iris Peppard&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Integrated Studies) founded Everyone&amp;rsquo;s Harvest 12 years ago through her senior capstone project. Since then, she has started the Marina Certified Farmers&amp;rsquo; Market, CSUMB Farm Stand and others. The Monterey County Weekly recently named her to its &amp;ldquo;25 for the Next 25&amp;rdquo; list of upcoming movers and shakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Summer Russell &lt;/strong&gt;(B.A., Liberal Studies) earned a master&amp;rsquo;s degree in elementary and secondary education from the University of California, Irvine, in 2005. Now an elementary teacher in Seal Beach, she loves teaching and encouraging students to go to college. She and &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Russell&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration &amp;rsquo;03) were married in August 2005 and have two children: Kai, 4, and Jake, 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2004&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Julie Marie&lt;/strong&gt; (Brown) Buck (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences) earned a Bachelor of Science degree in nursing from Rockhurst University and a Master of Science degree, also in nursing, from the University of Missouri, Kansas City. She now is a nurse practitioner with the Pediatric Group of Monterey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Jacob Cooney&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Teledramatic Arts &amp;amp; Technology), New York, is working as a clearance coordinator for the 20th Century Fox TV show, &amp;ldquo;Babylon Fields.&amp;rdquo; He also recently co-wrote the films &amp;ldquo;Apocalypse Pompeii&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;World&amp;rsquo;s End&amp;rdquo; for the Syfy channel with fellow TAT alumnus &lt;strong&gt;Bill Hanstock&lt;/strong&gt; (TAT &amp;rsquo;03). Jacob co-wrote and directed the feature film &amp;ldquo;Alpha House.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2005&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Doriana (Westerman) Hammond&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Integrated Studies) and her husband, Jeff, established Sun + Life Photography in 2010 in Santa Cruz. In 2013, the business was named one of Rangefinder Magazine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;30 Rising Stars in Wedding Photography.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Malinda DeRouen Mueller&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Teledramatic Arts &amp;amp; Technology) was a singer with Royal Caribbean cruise line for two years after graduation. Returning to Monterey, she continued to do theater and started a band. She opened for the Preservation Hall Jazz Band at the Sunset Center and starred in &amp;ldquo;Chicago&amp;rdquo; at the Western Stage in Salinas and &amp;ldquo;Spamalot&amp;rdquo; at the Pacific Repertory Theatre in Carmel. She married her college sweetheart, &lt;strong&gt;Douglas Mueller&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., TAT &amp;rsquo;03). They met while doing plays (&amp;ldquo;Grease&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Santos and Santos&amp;rdquo;) at the World Theater in 1999. They have a 3-year-old son, Leonard. Malinda and her family moved to Oakland last October after she was hired as a performer with &amp;ldquo;Beach Blanket Babylon&amp;rdquo; in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Kali Faye Viker&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences) attended graduate school at Chapman University&amp;rsquo;s Monterey campus, earning a master&amp;rsquo;s degree in human resources. She then joined Monterey Peninsula College as a human resources specialist and was promoted to HR analyst. Recently married, she and her husband share their new home in Seaside with two puppies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Meghan Lewis&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) and Aaron Nousaine (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences &amp;rsquo;06) recently announced their engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2007&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Katelyn Bryant&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Liberal Studies) was a member of the first Master of Social Work graduating class. She now is director of an emergency women&amp;rsquo;s shelter in Salinas&amp;rsquo; Chinatown, Women Alive! The shelter is run by Dorothy&amp;rsquo;s Place, which converts facilities that serve homeless people by day into a women-only shelter at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Ren Herring&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration) is an academic affairs administrator and adviser at New York University. During his tenure at NYU, Ren has founded and created several co-curricular programs to help new students adjust to the university. He has a master&amp;rsquo;s degree in administration, leadership and technology from NYU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2008&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Dana Arvig&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) works as director of client services for Moxxy Marketing in Salinas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Maria S. Ceja&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication), Marina, is assistant director of recruitment in the CSUMB Office of Admissions. Maria also serves on the CSUMB Alumni Board of Directors. She is engaged to &lt;strong&gt;Efrem Valentin&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Telecommunications, Multimedia and Applied Computing &amp;rsquo;06).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Ashley Chavez&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration) is senior marketing manager at Revinate in New York City. She is a regular guest speaker on the topics of digital marketing, social media and reputation management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Jennifer Dority&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) is a real estate agent for Coldwell Banker, where she enjoys helping people achieve their goals. Jennifer volunteers with the Professional Women&amp;rsquo;s Network, the CSUMB Alumni Board of Directors and the Surf Rider Foundation. She lives in Monterey and enjoys snowboarding, running and going for walks on Carmel Beach with her boyfriend, Charles, and dog, Sitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Michael Leslie&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Teledramatic Arts &amp;amp; Technology) landed internships, then a staff position with the Golden State Warriors. Since the 2010-11 season, Michael has worked for the basketball team as a production assistant &amp;mdash; a self-described &amp;ldquo;jack of all trades.&amp;rdquo; He helps the team&amp;rsquo;s radio producer compile sound bites from players and others around the league. He also works on video production, using skills he learned at CSUMB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Janie Parra-Salaz&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Collaborative Health and Human Services) is a crisis services manager at the Monterey County Rape Crisis Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Samira Perry&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration) is marketing and membership director at the Salinas Valley Chamber of Commerce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2009&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Nicole Charles&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Global Studies) is a district representative for state Sen. Bill Monning. She serves as president of CSUMB&amp;rsquo;s Alumni Board of Directors and is active with other community organizations. She lives in Monterey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Ashlie (Weisbly) McCallon&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Integrated Studies) earned a Master of Counseling degree from State Jose State University in 2013. First employed as a student assistant in the CSUMB Financial Aid Office, Ashlie now is a staff counselor there. She and her husband, Nick, live in Marina with their two dogs. They enjoy boating, skiing and weekend barbecues with friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Elisabeth Fagan&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Global Studies) is a client services specialist at Community Health Plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Karen Hagman&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration), Seaside, is a philanthropy officer at the Hartnell College Foundation, where she works with community leaders to positively impact the lives of students. She and &lt;strong&gt;Brian Stettenbenz&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication, &amp;rsquo;12) have summer wedding plans. She enjoys hiking with her dogs, wine tasting and gardening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Courtney Hermann&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Kinesiology), Redondo Beach, is owner and holistic nutrition coach at Healthy Makeovers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthymakeovers.com&quot; title=&quot;www.healthymakeovers.com&quot;&gt;www.healthymakeovers.com&lt;/a&gt;). She is enrolled in yoga teacher training and is involved in the Leukemia &amp;amp; Lymphoma Society&amp;rsquo;s Man &amp;amp; Woman of the Year fundraising campaign. She enjoys spending time with her longtime boyfriend, &lt;strong&gt;Kyle Satow&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Kinesiology &amp;rsquo;09), and her &amp;ldquo;little yorkie-poo,&amp;rdquo; Mikey, as well as going to the beach, going on bike rides and practicing yoga on her stand-up paddle board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Brian Stettenbenz&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) is digital media coordinator for the Monterey Plaza Hotel &amp;amp; Spa. He is engaged to &lt;strong&gt;Karen Hagman&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration &amp;rsquo;09).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2010&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Lauren Axworthy&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) recently was hired as an account executive at Yelp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Sven Brendel&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences, Master of Public Policy &amp;rsquo;12) is a project specialist at the Central California Alliance for Health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Alimata Coulibaly&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration) is a grants officer at Save the Children in the U.S.-Sahel office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Steven Goings&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences) was honored Feb. 22 at the Crystal Ball, an annual event that benefits the education and prevention programs of Central Coast HIV/AIDS Services. Steven was honored for his work promoting AIDS awareness and prevention at CSUMB during 2010-12, when he served as the university&amp;rsquo;s purposeful service coordinator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Chanel Hason&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Environmental Science, Technology and Policy) represented the United States as Miss Scuba USA in the Miss Scuba International 2013 pageant in December in Malaysia. &amp;ldquo;My purpose in life is to educate as many people as possible about ways to protect our planet, and this opportunity with the pageant seemed like a step in the right direction,&amp;rdquo; she said. Chanel was second runner-up in the contest and was named Miss Best Diver and Miss Marine Conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Adriana Melgoza&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) received an award of merit in the staff support category at the Legal Aid Association of California&amp;rsquo;s 30th anniversary celebration Jan. 31 in San Francisco. Adriana works for the Watsonville Law Center, where she manages the center&amp;rsquo;s legal clinics and recruits, trains and supervises volunteers. Those volunteers include CSUMB service learners, which is how Adriana got her start at the WLC in 2009. She excelled in the position, earning the Human Communication Service Learning award the next year. After graduation, the WLC hired her. Her duties also include community education around legal issues and staff training for community organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Josh Williams&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Business Administration) is food service sales coordinator and analytical support at Driscoll&amp;rsquo;s. His duties include managing million-dollar accounts, processing and maintaining accounts receivable files, and providing customer support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2011&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Marie Beard&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Business Administration) is a certified public accountant at Hayashi &amp;amp; Wayland. Previously a sergeant in the U.S. Army Reserve, she enjoys marathon running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Christie Waterford&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Communication Design) is a junior graphic designer at Power Brands in Southern California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2012&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Haley Hernandez&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Human Communication) is a project coordinator at idX Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Tacia Williams&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Global Studies) moved in 2012 to New York City, where she is enrolled in the Sociology of Education program at New York University. Also a dancer and Zumba instructor, Tacia traveled to Uganda with NYU in January, studying traditional dance and working with children through local organizations. &amp;ldquo;When I lived in Puerto Rico for a short time in 2010 through CSUMB,&amp;rdquo; she writes, &amp;ldquo;I learned the power of community through dance. Studying there was one of the biggest leaps I took, and my life has been influenced by that decision since then.&amp;rdquo; Tacia serves as the director of multicultural education on the Sigma Theta Psi national board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;
	2013&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Andrew S. Lopez&lt;/strong&gt; (B.A., Social and Behavioral Sciences) completed five months of training to become a police officer. He has been employed with the Gilroy Police Department since October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Ryan T. Scott&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Kinesiology) received a graduate assistantship in San Jose State University&amp;rsquo;s kinesiology master&amp;rsquo;s program. He now is a strength coach for the Monterey Sports Center and the Monterey Police Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Linda Werre&lt;/strong&gt; (B.S., Environmental Studies) is a trained marine archaeologist and scientific diver, after attending Maritime Archaeology School in St. Augustine, Fla. She recently married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Submit a &lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/classnote&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Class Note&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/324">Alumni News</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/17">Alumni Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/25">Community</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 02:18:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21326 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>The Grapes of Tech</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/grapes-tech</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Scheid Vineyards&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/30-scheid-vineyard.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	Alumni use skills learned at CSUMB for &amp;lsquo;precision viticulture&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By PATIA STEPHENS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	Gregory Gonzalez (SBS &amp;rsquo;09) and Jonathan Vevoda (SBS &amp;rsquo;12) launched their careers at CSU Monterey Bay. The two alumni use geographic information systems (GIS) skills they learned at CSUMB in their jobs at Scheid Vineyards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Maps produced with GIS&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/30-scheid-map.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;A world-class winery headquartered in Greenfield, Scheid Vineyards comprises 13 ranches with 4,200 acres producing 38,000 tons of grapes a year &amp;ndash; resulting in some 40 million gallons of wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Gonzalez and Vevoda, with their boss Tyler Scheid, are at the forefront of the emerging &amp;ldquo;precision viticulture&amp;rdquo; industry, in which GIS and other high-tech tools turn the art of winemaking into a profitable &amp;ndash; and palatable &amp;ndash; science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Both majored in Social and Behavioral Sciences and started at Scheid as interns, becoming full-time employees after graduation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Gonzalez came to CSUMB as a soccer player transferring from Oregon. He turned to GIS after receiving some good advising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Sharon Anderson emailed me and said, if you take one more class, you can get a minor in Environmental Science,&amp;rdquo; Gonzalez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	He started at Scheid in 2009, using global positioning systems (GPS) and GIS to remap boundaries, label &amp;ldquo;blocks&amp;rdquo; of vines and estimate crop yields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	A Salinas High School graduate, Vevoda earned a concentration in GIS after his research revealed it was one of the top emerging career paths. GIS combines his interests in the outdoors, maps and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Greg Gonzalez and Jon Vevoda&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/30-scheid-jon-greg.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s a good balance between working on computers and working in the field,&amp;rdquo; Vevoda said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	His first project for Scheid &amp;ndash; also his senior capstone project &amp;ndash; was developing a harvest safety rating system, the first of its kind. The program measures and rates slopes, which helps the winery prevent accidents by allocating more experienced personnel to steeper sections. Identifying slope, along with aspect (slope direction) and solar radiation, also helps with vineyard site selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;I can look at a location and tell whether this lot will get fruit ripe when we need it to be,&amp;rdquo; Vevoda said. &amp;ldquo;If we can see it&amp;rsquo;s going to be in shade by 2 o&amp;rsquo;clock, it&amp;rsquo;s probably not a good place to plant vines.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Efficiency is the goal of precision viticulture, Gonzalez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what you can do with a smartphone,&amp;rdquo; Gonzalez said. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re all engineers. Farmers are engineers. We&amp;rsquo;re turning data into information you can act on.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://scheidvineyards.com&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;scheidvineyards.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photos: Vineyard and map courtesy Scheid Vineyards; bottom photo by Patia Stephens&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/324">Alumni News</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/17">Alumni Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/24">Innovation</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 02:06:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21325 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>News Briefs</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/news-briefs</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	New nursing program accommodates working professionals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Stack of nursing books&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/28-nursing.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	CSU Monterey Bay is expanding its nursing program. Starting in June, the program will add a track for already-employed nurses with associate&amp;rsquo;s degrees who want to earn a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s while they continue to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Classes will be held in the late afternoons and evenings; some will be traditional face-to-face classes, some will be online. The curriculum will include courses on research methods, evidence-based practice, health policy, informatics, genomics and chronic care management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Classes will be offered throughout the year; students can graduate in 14 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	In addition to nurses who are currently employed, the program will admit recent community college nursing graduates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;The idea is for a seamless transition from community college to CSUMB,&amp;rdquo; said Dr. Marianne Hultgren, interim director of nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The university started its nursing program in 2012, in partnership with four local community colleges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/nursing&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;csumb.edu/nursing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;shy;&lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Joan Weiner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	Summer Arts returns to campus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Student with guitar&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/28-summer-arts.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;CSU Summer Arts returns to campus for a third year in late June with a lineup of 16 classes and dozens of public events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Students &amp;ndash; who come from CSU campuses, other four-year and two-year colleges as well as the local community &amp;ndash; are immersed in rigorous training up to 12 hours a day during the two-week sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Classes are offered in dance, music, theater, creative writing, visual arts and filmmaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Public events include lectures, concerts and theatrical productions, all priced to make them accessible to a wide audience. In addition, each course concludes with a free public performance or &amp;ldquo;culmination,&amp;rdquo; where students showcase their talents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	A list of classes is available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://csusummerarts.org&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;csusummerarts.org&lt;/a&gt;. The schedule of public performances will be announced in late May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Joan Weiner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/multimedia&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Watch a video about Summer Arts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	President&amp;rsquo;s Speaker Series helps Monterey County flourish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;President&amp;#039;s Speaker Series speakers&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/29-pss.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;With a theme of &amp;ldquo;Flourish Monterey County,&amp;rdquo; this year&amp;rsquo;s President&amp;rsquo;s Speaker Series at CSU Monterey Bay provided fresh insights into the challenges faced by local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The series opened March 4 with a presentation by Mary Jo Waits, director of the Economic, Human Services and Workforce Division of the National Governors Association. Her topic was &amp;ldquo;Leveraging Universities in Regional Economic Development.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	David Kennedy, former director of the Boston Gun Project, followed with a March 28 talk on &amp;ldquo;Gangs, Guns and Growth: Finding Alternatives to Violence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Jeff Edmondson, managing director of Strive Together, spoke April 9 on &amp;ldquo;Collective Impact: A New Way of Doing Business to Improve Educational Outcomes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The theme of next spring&amp;rsquo;s series will be &amp;ldquo;Future Monterey.&amp;rdquo; Speakers will examine how the county&amp;rsquo;s economy can be diversified beyond agriculture and tourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Joan Weiner&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	CalStateTEACH pairs first-graders with teacher candidates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Tutor and first-grader&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/29-calstateteach.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;Each June for the past four years, 20 first-grade students from Highland Elementary have joined with 20 teaching credential candidates from Cal StateTEACH in a unique summer tutorial endeavor at King Elementary School in Seaside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The Summer Literacy Lab School Partnership provides invaluable instruction for students not making adequate progress during the regular academic year, as well as high-quality mentoring for the teacher candidates tutoring them. The 16-day program is a partnership between CalStateTEACH and Monterey Peninsula Unified School District.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The mostly limited-English-speaking students receive one-on-one support in reading and language arts. The tutors first administer assessments from CalStateTEACH&amp;rsquo;s Literacy Case Study, then design instruction to close the literacy gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Roger Dahl, the CSUMB lecturer who designed and leads the CalStateTEACH program, worked with MPUSD personnel to address the need for focused instruction for the English-learner population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	During the summer program, the student teachers receive daily mentoring from two literacy experts from MPUSD, who provide guidance on the best strategies and practices and offer immediate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Results from the first four summers have been impressive, with students in many cases making progress equal to what they achieved during the school year in only three weeks of focused instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Roger Dahl&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Images, top to bottom: provided; Joan Iguban Galiguis; Jeffrey Lewis; Roger Dahl&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/18">Staff/Faculty Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/64">University News</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/21">Excellence</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 02:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21324 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Thinking Different</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/thinking-different</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	Johanna Poethig keeps the vision of VPA alive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By PATIA STEPHENS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	As one of CSU Monterey Bay&amp;rsquo;s founding faculty members, Professor Johanna Poethig has been with the Visual &amp;amp; Public Art Department since its inception in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Johanna Poethig with mural&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/27-johanna-poethig.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;The VPA program was one of the first in the country that emphasized not just the visual, but also the social aspects of art education.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;The beauty of this program is that we do both,&amp;rdquo; Poethig said. &amp;ldquo;Students come here, they gotta learn skills. They have to learn how to be studio artists, and think about their personal creativity and creative growth. But they do that within a curriculum of thinking about how art takes place in a social context.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Born in New Jersey and raised in Manila, Philippines, Poethig earned degrees from the University of California, Santa Cruz, and Mills College. She&amp;rsquo;s been in California since 1976, forging an eclectic career out of a variety of interests and mediums, from painting and sculpture to performance art and video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a lot of different things,&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s just who I am. ... Rather than choose, I do it all.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;
	Her installations include dozens of large-scale murals, many of which transform urban blight into pockets of color and meaning. In her Painting and Mural class, students are working on a vivid, 300-foot-long mural in the rural farmworker community of Pajaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;This community has had nothing &amp;ndash; no place for the kids to play, no place for the community to get together,&amp;rdquo; Poethig said. The new park is &amp;ldquo;really kind of amazing &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s like an oasis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Public art education develops skills useful in any career, like creativity and teamwork, Poethig said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;The main thing about artists is that we&amp;rsquo;re not literal all the time,&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re creative, so we&amp;rsquo;re divergent thinkers. That&amp;rsquo;s a very important part of learning. If you just train [students] in a linear fashion, they&amp;rsquo;ll never become as creative as when you help them make connections that are surprising. It&amp;rsquo;s only by making those unlikely connections that you get innovative ideas.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Another project is renewal of the campus &amp;ldquo;Signs and Symbols&amp;rdquo; mural, which was removed for lead abatement. Poethig is leading the effort, which will involve faculty members, students and alumni in planning and painting a new version of the beloved mural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;It will reflect on the vision of the university and draw upon the old design,&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;You don&amp;rsquo;t want to forget your history, but you also want to look toward the future.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http:johannapoethig.com&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;johannapoethig.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photo by Chris Brown&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/63">Feature</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/18">Staff/Faculty Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/28">Vision</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:53:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21323 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Faculty Adviser</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/faculty-adviser</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	Why the&amp;nbsp;Humanities Matter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By REN&amp;Eacute;E CURRY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	A former student of mine, whose husband has been living with a brain tumor for over a decade, highly values the science and technology that keeps her husband alive, but when asked how she copes day-to-day in this world, she talks about catharsis and the crucial role of the humanities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Renée Curry&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/26-renee-curry.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;&amp;ldquo;In 1842, Ralph Waldo Emerson lost his 5-year old son,&amp;rdquo; my former student said. &amp;ldquo;His poem about the loss, &amp;lsquo;Threnody,&amp;rsquo; provides me a waypoint for my own struggles. Across time, Emerson reaches out and helps me navigate through the desolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Another work, the &amp;lsquo;Epic of Gilgamesh,&amp;rsquo; comforts me when I sit in the intensive care unit listening to my husband breathe and hoping he will continue to breathe another day. Gilgamesh&amp;rsquo;s solitary vigil with Enkidu&amp;rsquo;s body shows me that over 4,000 years ago, someone felt what I feel today.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	This experience of catharsis &amp;mdash; the purifying and purgation of emotion, first described by Aristotle &amp;mdash; is one of the most profound gifts of the humanities. It is real and transformative. Catharsis heightens our understanding of the world; it redirects and improves our ways of thinking and understanding; it enhances our ability to reflect upon our lives and the lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	People very much like us, and yet not like us at all, have existed on this planet and have generously preserved and shared literatures, histories, artifacts, languages, laws, cultural practices, religions, and philosophies. These convey first-hand the depths of worlds outside our own limited universe, the complex emotions of differing beings, and the moral and ethical questions that drive the conscience and logic of a time. The humanities honors and preserves this material. Study of the humanities teaches us to exercise the reflection, communication, analysis and interpretation necessary to understand these words, artifacts and cultural practices from a multitude of perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The words of Martin Luther King Jr. provide a lens into a life worth living when he writes, &amp;ldquo;An individual has not started living until he can rise above the narrow confines of his individual concerns to the broader concerns of humanity.&amp;rdquo; The humanities offer a diverse set of lenses for looking at the world, lenses that enable us to develop empathy, compassion, and connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The humanities provide us with ways to frame the current real world, as well as ways to engage with this world as valuable citizens. Study of the humanities empowers us to apply ourselves rigorously in this world, to work at being present and productive, and to contribute to humanity by making meaning where there sometimes seems to be none. The humanities ultimately provide refuge for us in our darkest times and helps us understand what it means to be merely, and significantly, human. &lt;strong&gt;MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;Ren&amp;eacute;e Curry is a professor in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hcom.csumb.edu&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Division of Humanities and Communication&lt;/a&gt; at CSU Monterey Bay. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photo by Randy Tunnell&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/63">Feature</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/18">Staff/Faculty Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/28">Vision</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:47:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21322 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Favorite Activity in the United States  (So Far...)</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/favorite-activity-united-states-so-far</link>
    <description> &lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By SARA SANTINI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure what a ropes challenge course was, but it sounded like fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Sara Santini on ropes course&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/24-santini-ropes.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; /&gt;I arrived at the course, which was organized by Outdoor Recreation and is in the woods surrounding campus. It looked like a lot of high wooden pillars with ropes between them. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen one back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;You wanna try this one?&amp;rdquo; asked the course leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	She showed me a pillar that was separated from the others. It turned out to be one of the most challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;So, what you do is just climb up to the top,&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;It gets a bit wiggly and windy on the top, but when you get there, you should stand up straight on the top of the pillar.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;And then?&amp;rdquo; I asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Then you jump!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I decided not to think about it too much. I started climbing. The only thing I could hold onto was the pillar; it had small steps, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard to climb. Apart from that, I just had my security rope for getting down. I was on my own. When I got to the top, it was kind of scary to stand up &amp;ndash; the wind was blowing and the pillar was shaky. I stood up and looked around. The view was really cool: It was foggy, so all I saw was green trees and fog. Usually, you can see the ocean from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Now just jump!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I looked down and realized I was really high, and I had nothing but the rope on my back. It all happened a bit fast and unexpectedly, so I felt kind of surprised to find myself all the way up there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	But I jumped!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Sara Santini&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/24-sara-santini.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;And it was so nice, and exciting. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even feel the impact on my back from jumping, because of all the belts I had on me. I slowly came down, and the girl congratulated me and unhooked the rope from my belt. My legs felt a bit shaky from the adrenaline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The shaky legs didn&amp;rsquo;t help when I tried the next challenge, where I climbed up an even higher pillar and had to get to the other one by crossing over a wooden log. Being so high without anything to hold onto makes you nervous, which makes you panic and lose your balance. I thought the course would be more physically challenging, but in fact, it was mostly a mental challenge of overcoming the boundaries you set for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I really liked the one you do in a pair: You and your partner cross the distance between pillars over a thin rope, without anything to hold on to. In order to get from one bar to another, you have to work with your partner &amp;mdash; they hold you while you let go of the bar and walk to the next one. When you reach it, you help your partner across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	I felt so confident about myself! I got so confident that at the end I even did the challenge with the log once more, but blindfolded. I realized it was all in my head. I was actually very secure, so I needed to calm my mind and trust my abilities. You can&amp;rsquo;t let yourself panic. You must trust yourself and just start going. &lt;strong&gt;MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;Sara Santini is an exchange student from Serbia, where she is a senior majoring in film editing. This essay was excerpted from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.worldlearning.org/global-gazette/2013/12/02/favorite-activity-in-the-united-states-so-far/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Global Gazette&lt;/a&gt;, which is published by the Global Undergraduate Exchange Program. The program is sponsored by the U.S. Department of State Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs and implemented by World Learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photos: (top) Marilaine Savard; (bottom) Wassim Zoghlami&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/63">Feature</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/16">Student Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/26">Diversity</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:31:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21321 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Outdoor Recreation</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/outdoor-recreation</link>
    <description> &lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	Many students are attracted to CSU Monterey Bay because of the ample opportunities for outdoor recreation on and near campus. The university&amp;rsquo;s Outdoor Recreation program is thriving, with students participating in outings and activities such as backpacking, camping, rock climbing, mountain biking, skiing, kayaking, surfing and stand-up paddleboarding. Here is a collection of photos from recent trips to Big Sur, Yosemite and Pinnacles national parks, Sugar Bowl Resort and the Ventana Wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Two surfers at Big Sur&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/22-surfers.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Skiers&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/22-skiing.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Rock climber at Pinnacles&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/22-climbing.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Student jumping on beach&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/22-student-jumping.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Yosemite waterfall&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/22-waterfall.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Students hiking at Yosemite&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/22-yosemite-campers.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/outdoor-rec&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;csumb.edu/outdoor-rec&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/multimedia&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watch videos about the Outdoor Recreation program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	All photos by Jarrett McAdams; except skiing photo by Mari Fukutomi&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/63">Feature</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/16">Student Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/28">Vision</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:26:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21320 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fresh Focus</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/fresh-focus</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	Kirby Garry brings changes to CSUMB athletics program&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By KEVIN GILMORE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	Since becoming director of athletics at Cal State Monterey Bay last November, Kirby Garry has already succeeded in shining a national spotlight on the university. He&amp;rsquo;s also quickly establishing Otter Athletics as a national leader in social media marketing, while maintaining its commitment to academic achievement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Kirby Garry being interviewed by Cat Anderson of CBS Sports&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/20-kirby-garry-interview.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; /&gt;Garry began his term as interim director of athletics July 8, replacing Vince Otoupal, who left to become director of athletics at NCAA Division I member Utah Valley University. CSUMB Vice President for Student Affairs Ronnie Higgs made the appointment permanent on Nov. 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Garry joined the Otter Athletics team in 2008 as assistant athletics director of external operations. His areas of oversight have included all aspects of athletics communications, corporate partnerships, development and marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Garry graduated cum laude with a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in social science from the University of North Dakota and earned his master&amp;rsquo;s in athletics administration from the University of South Dakota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Arriving at CSUMB with strong experience as an administrator, coach and student&amp;ndash;athlete, Garry served in athletics administration roles at both Washington State University and Idaho State University after four years as an assistant football coach at USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;We talk a lot about making the big-time where you are, and for us, big-time starts in the classroom,&amp;rdquo; Garry said. &amp;ldquo;More than 60 percent of our student&amp;ndash;athletes carry a cumulative grade-point average of 3.0 or greater. By percentage, we have more students win conference academic honors from the California Collegiate Athletic Association than any other institution.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The Otters also have hung more than their share of championship banners around campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Kirby Garry&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/20-kirby-garry-mug.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;&amp;ldquo;Despite being the youngest institution &amp;mdash; not athletic program, institution &amp;mdash; in all of NCAA Division II sports,&amp;rdquo; he said, &amp;ldquo;we already have won an NCAA national title [men&amp;rsquo;s golf in 2011] and have 14 CCAA titles in seven years as a conference member.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Those successes helped bring another honor to CSUMB when the Otter women&amp;rsquo;s basketball team hosted Cal State San Bernardino in a Feb. 15 game broadcast on the CBS Sports Network. It&amp;rsquo;s not often that a small school gets to host a live, nationally televised game on a major sports network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Garry was instrumental in making that happen, working behind the scenes with NCAA leadership to help CSUMB earn a spot as one of eight Division II basketball programs to host a game on CBS this year. In fact, it was Garry&amp;rsquo;s status as a national leader in NCAA social media development that led to the game being designated the Division II Social Media Game of the Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The NCAA sent a production crew to document CSUMB&amp;rsquo;s uses of social media for a &amp;ldquo;best practices&amp;rdquo; piece to be presented at the national convention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re always looking for ways to gain a little ground or to separate ourselves,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;Social media offers us a free platform with multiple ways of doing that. We stood out enough that the NCAA decided to shine a spotlight here.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://otterathletics.com&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;otterathletics.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	Photos by Vernon McKnight&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/91">athletics</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/18">Staff/Faculty Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/64">University News</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/24">Innovation</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:22:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21319 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Where Art and Science Converge</title>
    <link>http://magazine.csumb.edu/news/2014/may/21/where-art-and-science-converge</link>
    <description> &lt;h3&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Illustration of wild roses by Jane Kim&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/large/164/attachments/news/images/14-wild-roses.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
	CSUMB&amp;#39;s Science Illustration Program&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	By JOAN WEINER&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;
	A four-month residency at the San Francisco dump changed the direction of Jane Kim&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	There, the graduate of the Rhode Island School of Design used construction scrap to investigate how walls &amp;ndash; and the way we decorate them &amp;ndash; can have damaging environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	That gave her a purpose, she said, &amp;ldquo;beyond art for art&amp;rsquo;s sake.&amp;rdquo; Inspired by science and the natural world, Kim decided to pursue a certificate from CSU Monterey Bay&amp;rsquo;s graduate-level science illustration program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Artist Jane Kim&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/14-jane-kim.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;Today, Kim is working on a series called &amp;ldquo;Migrating Mural,&amp;rdquo; a collection of images painted along migration corridors of endangered species. Through the murals, she said, the transient life of these animals can easily be seen, and more importantly, appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Jane has found ways to take what she loves and do some magnificent work,&amp;rdquo; said Ann Caudle, director of the science illustration program. &amp;ldquo;She has found her own niche.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So have many of the program&amp;rsquo;s graduates, who work for publications such as Scientific American and National Geographic; museums, such as the Smithsonian and the American Museum of Natural History; and at zoos, botanical gardens and aquariums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Science illustration has been around a very long time. Roman coins &amp;ndash; with their representations of plants that still exist &amp;ndash; are early examples. Leonardo&amp;rsquo;s human anatomy studies and Galileo&amp;rsquo;s drawings of the moon&amp;rsquo;s cratered surface are other examples. Illustrators accompanied Captain Cook and Charles Darwin on their expeditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Even the binomial classification system created by Linnaeus &amp;ndash; and still in use &amp;ndash; was introduced to the world through the work of a science illustrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Ask Caudle why the discipline is still relevant &amp;ndash; given that everyone has a camera-equipped cell phone &amp;ndash; and the answer comes quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;Honeycreepers illustration by Jane Kim&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/14-honeycreepers.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left&quot; /&gt;&amp;ldquo;Illustrations can show us the inside of a tornado,&amp;rdquo; she said by way of example. &amp;ldquo;And photos won&amp;rsquo;t allow us to go back in time to see species that existed in the past.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Jenny Keller, an instructor in the program, added that illustrations and animations explain new technologies and advancements in science to the scientific community, as well as to the curious public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The work is all around us, if we just look &amp;ndash; in books and field guides; adorning the walls of natural history museums; gracing exhibit labels to help aquarium visitors tell the difference between a sea lion and an otter; on interpretive signs in parks and nature preserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	The program started at UC Santa Cruz in the 1980s and moved to CSUMB in 2009. It accepts 15 students a year among the 50 or so who apply; they complete an academic year of classes and a 10-week internship. They learn to sketch in the field and to design information graphics and interactive displays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Complementing the skills-based courses are instruction in copyright, contract law and other real-world topics. Students produce business cards and build portfolios while learning how to pitch clients and publishers &amp;ndash; since many of them will work as freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Because of the broad range of skills and their versatility and flexibility, our graduates have quite an edge out there,&amp;rdquo; Caudle said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Applicants include art students and people with a background in science. That&amp;rsquo;s not an odd combination. Both art and science are about close observation, Caudle said, and the mix is beneficial for both groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Artists look at things in a different way than scientists,&amp;rdquo; Caudle said. &amp;ldquo;They look at color composition. That&amp;rsquo;s fabulous for the science students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;The learning, the training, a lot of it is the rich mix of people in the program.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;img alt=&quot;White-lipped peccary illustration by Jane Kim&quot; src=&quot;http://magazine.csumb.edu/sites/default/files/imagecache/medium/164/attachments/news/images/14-peccary.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:right&quot; /&gt;Corlis Schneider, who earned a certificate from the program in 2011, combined interests in both science and art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re younger, you don&amp;rsquo;t think there is a way to reconcile a love for art and science,&amp;rdquo; she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;So you grow up focusing on science, like I did, or art.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	While earning a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in marine biology from UC Santa Cruz, she realized that her favorite classes were the labs where students had to illustrate their specimens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	That led her to CSUMB&amp;rsquo;s program. &amp;ldquo;It was clearly the right decision for me,&amp;rdquo; she said. She&amp;rsquo;s now a Los Angeles-based freelance illustrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Julie Naylor Selan, a 2011 graduate of the program, is another L.A-based freelancer. She specializes in wildlife and paleontological illustration in traditional and digital media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;ldquo;Growing up, my weekends were spent in aquariums, museums, at the zoo or out on hikes,&amp;rdquo; she said. At 15, she was certified as a scuba diver and &amp;ldquo;that opened up a whole new world.&amp;rdquo; She, too, found her way to the science illustration program. &amp;ldquo;It was life-changing for me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Kim shares the view. &amp;quot;The science illustration program was one of the most important decisions of my life,&amp;quot; Kim said. &amp;quot;Through the program, I was able to define what sort of purpose art had for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;quot;I learned new techniques, refined old ones and left the program feeling very prepared,&amp;quot; she said. MB&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://scienceillustration.org&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;scienceillustration.org&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://ink-dwell.com&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;ink-dwell.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://csumb.edu/multimedia &quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Watch video of Jane Kim&lt;/a&gt; talking about her inspiration for the Migrating Mural series&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;small&quot;&gt;
	All illustrations by Jane Kim; photo of Jane Kim by Kelly Hsaio&lt;/p&gt;
 </description>
     <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/324">Alumni News</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/17">Alumni Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/alumni-story">Alumni Story</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/56">Magazine</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/8">Potential Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/category/news-tags/v7n1">v7n1</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/1">Students</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/4">Donors</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/21">Excellence</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/2">Parents</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/3">Alumni</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/5">Community Members</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/7">Faculty</category>
 <category domain="http://magazine.csumb.edu/taxonomy/term/6">Staff</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 01:12:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>step5946</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21318 at http://magazine.csumb.edu</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>